Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. So today's דף Daf is דף כ.
Daf Chaf. So דף כ Daf Chaf and we pick up about
10 lines down. Again, we're the דף Daf behind but God-willing we
will catch up. I'll tell you the plan later. Anyway, so 10
lines down at the two dots, יהודה מכשיר בקטן. Yehuda Machshir Be'Katan.
So we're dealing with who reads the מגילה. Megillah. We had a
whole discussion about somebody who was deaf and couldn't hear what he
was saying and now we deal with the case of a קטן,
Katan, a minor, which is bizarre because normally minors cannot are not
obligated and therefore cannot discharge other people's obligations but רב יהודה Reb
Yehuda says a קטן Katan is okay. Let's take a look at
the גמרא Gemara and earlier we actually made a distinction between the
קטן שהגיע לחינוך Katan Shehiggia Lachinuch and not הגיע לחינוך, Higgia Lachinuch,
of the age of training or not. So the גמרא Gemara doesn't
really unpack that. Let's read the גמרא Gemara and then I'll say
a word about that. Okay, דתניא Detanya we taught in a ברייתא.
Braisa. אמר רב יהודה Amar Reb Yehuda קטן הייתי וקריתיה למעלה מרב
טרפון והזקנים בלוד. Katan Hayiti Vekiritia Lemala meReb Tarfon Vehazekeinim beLod. He
says בלוד, beLod, he said here's my proof, I was a minor
and I read the מגילה Megillah in לוד Lod in the presence
of רב טרפון Reb Tarfon and the
elders and presumably למעלה's Lemala an interesting point, like maybe it means
that he was on a raised platform and reading it. Yeah, so
I mean there's this whole יורד לפני התיבה Yoreid Lifnei Hateivah but
that's actually people think that that means like this idea of this
indent in the ground which actually is not the case because there's
no evidence of that in the ancient architecture. Anyway, it might mean
that the ארון Aron was at a higher place. It's discussed about
where the ארון Aron was located vis-à-vis where the שליח ציבור Sheliach
Tzibbur was. Okay, but anyway, and I read it in the presence
of רב טרפון Reb Tarfon and the elders. אמרו לו Amru Lo
they said to him, אין מביאין ראיה מן הקטן. Ein Mevi’im Re’aya
Min Hakatan. Ah, you were a minor so we can't take the
testimony of a minor.
Which is a pretty convenient response.
So it reminds me of I was reading about like the Roe
v. Wade decision and you know initially basically they wanted to the
some of the those that were
opposing any change in the abortion law wanted to refuse to see
that the case should be heard by the Supreme Court because by
the time it would anything would get to the Supreme Court the
woman would have already had the baby, would no longer be able
to have an abortion, so therefore she had no standing so therefore
she couldn't bring the case to the court. So the same type
of a point, okay by the time it's whatever. Anyway, I saw
some parallel there. Anyway, okay you can't bring proof from a minor.
תניא Tanya we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, אמר רבי, Amar Rebbi,
קטן הייתי וקריתיה למעלה מרבי יהודה. Katan Hayiti Vekiritia Lemala meRebbi Yehuda.
I was a minor and I read it in the presence of
רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. So here's יהודה הנשיא Yehuda HaNasi saying it.
אמרו לו Amru Lo they said to him, אין מביאין ראיה מן
המתיר. Ein Mevi’im Re’aya Min Hamatir. You cannot bring proof from the
one who permits it. Of course רב יהודה Reb Yehuda was fine
with it, רב יהודה's Reb Yehuda the one who says a קטן
Katan can read, that doesn't there's no additional evidence. So the גמרא
Gemara says ולאימלויה V'loimulei אין מביאין ראיה מן הקטן. Ein Mevi’im Re’aya
Min Hakatan. How about the other response which is you were a
minor we can't take the testimony of a minor? So no, חדא
ועוד קאמרו ליה. Chada Ve'od Kamru Lo. They were saying one and
another. חדא Chada number one, דקטן היית Dekatan Hayisa number one you
were a minor so any testimony you give about what you did
when you were a minor is inadmissible. ועוד Ve'od and secondly, אפילו
גדול היית Afilu Gadol Hayisa even if you were an adult, which
of course then would make the whole case irrelevant, but let's say
you were a גדול Gadol observing some other קטן Katan who read
it in the presence of רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, אין מביאין ראיה
מן המתיר, Ein Mevi’im Re’aya Min Hamatir, you can't bring any proof
from the fact that the one who says it's permissible said it
was permissible. That doesn't mean a proof, a larger proof that anybody
acknowledged that it was permissible. So anyway, the issue is that so
the גמרא Gemara leaves it at that, it doesn't really analyze this
position of a קטן Katan but תוספות Tosafos basically spells it out
that since the reading of a מגילה Megillah is a rabbinic obligation
although it is interesting, you know some of the פוסקים Poskim and
the whatever מפרשים Mefarshim try to conceptualize a distinction between the מגילה
Megillah at night and the מגילה Megillah of the day. The מגילה
Megillah at night they say is a rabbinic obligation, the מגילה Megillah
of the day they frame as it's a מצווה מדברי סופרים Mitzvah
Midevrei Soferim so that's derived from the verses at a higher level
and again that's giving priority to the one at the day. But
anyway, but okay, it's clearly not either one is not biblical and
therefore maybe somebody who's only rabbinically obligated could discharge the obligation of
a rabbinic obligation. Of course, well תוספות Tosafos doesn't distinguish in this
regard but I was just adding that point in. But of course
that's not so clear from two perspectives. Number one is is that
it's what תוספות Tosafos calls and תוספות Tosafos recognizes this and just
points out why this is not so obvious and why it's problematic
is it's a double דרבנן, Derabbanan, meaning for the קטן Katan he's
rabbinically obligated in a דרבנן Derabbanan מצווה, Mitzvah, it puts him one
level lower in degrees of obligation than an adult who's obligated in
a דרבנן Derabbanan מצווה. Mitzvah. So just because we're all within rabbinic
territory doesn't mean all bets are off. The other interesting thing to
ask is when we say that there's that there's a rabbinic obligation
in terms of חינוך, Chinuch, who's rabbinically obligated? Right? Normally we think
that it's the parents. I mean there's a question, parents or
father the mother in terms of חינוך, Chinuch, another conversation. But normally
we think that it's the parents that are obligated
to be מחנך Mechanech their kids and to train their kids in
the מצוות. Mitzvos. To say that the kid is rabbinically obligated... it
is a little bit ironic, right? He's a minor, so he can't
be, he's not of an age where he can be biblically obligated,
but the rabbis obligated him. Well, what's the rabbis' power to obligate
him, if he's already excluded from the system of obligation? So, it's
a very funny idea, but some do understand that there is some
concept that he is rabbinically obligated to do it. And that seems
to fit in with this idea of Reb Yehuda (רבי יהודה). Reb
Yehuda Or another completely different approach is not to focus on the
sense of obligation and an individual discharging another individual's obligation, which is
normally the framework that we look at, but is to look at
it from the context of Pirsumei Nisa (פרסומי ניסא). Pirsumei Nisa You
know, there's the public reading of the Megilla (מגילה), Megilla the kiyum
(קיום) kiyum of Pirsumei Nisa (פרסומי ניסא). Pirsumei Nisa Maybe we don't
have to so much look at it like whose level of obligation,
you know, in that personal sense, more in the fact that this
public ritual took place. Think, for example, the idea, if we think
in this context of public ritual, that the who can get an
aliya (עליה)? aliya Right? The famous mishna (משנה) mishna says, right, which
actually we're going to get to, right, is in principle hakol olin
leminyan shiva (הכל עולין למניין שבע), hakol olin leminyan shiva right? And
it... well, no, be'emes amru (באמת אמרו), be'emes amru right, that an
isha (אשה) isha can get an aliya (עליה), aliya katan (קטן) katan
can get an aliya (עליה). aliya There's issues of kevod hatzibur (כבוד
הציבור), kevod hatzibur but the normal principles of like mitzvas asei shehazman
grama (מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמא) mitzvas asei shehazman grama or bar hiyuva
(בר חיובא) bar hiyuva and being an adult don't really apply. Fundamentally,
there's a much broader range of who can get an aliya (עליה)
aliya because maybe you're not looking at it as personal obligation and
discharging my personal obligation and you have to have the same level.
Maybe we're just looking at it as a certain type of a
communal ritual and therefore maybe anybody, you know, can participate in it.
So that's a certain... that's I think an interesting other way of
thinking of the katan (קטן). katan It would still raise the question
then why exclude even the cheiresh (חרש) cheiresh and the shoteh (שוטה)?
shoteh But maybe you could say that their type of reading is
of a different quality, you know, if they're not able to hear
what you're saying or if whatever. So, anyway, it's a... interesting question
about whether the mishna (משנה) mishna maybe something completely different is going
on here in the context of it being not a private reading,
maybe a private reading would be different, but a public reading and
maybe something about the whole Pirsumei Nisa (פרסומי ניסא) Pirsumei Nisa aspect
of it that makes you think differently in then the sense of
personal obligation. That's an idea I'm putting out there, but again, it
bears further investigation. We don't rule like Reb Yehuda (רבי יהודה), Reb
Yehuda so the whole point is moot, okay? No, I mean you
give katan aliya (קטן עליה) katan aliya to some places, so like
Sefardi (ספרדי) Sefardi communities they give katan maftir (קטן מפטיר) katan maftir
and so on, right? So that's... so okay, so if you like
the idea I was putting out there, hold off, we'll re-discuss it
when we get to krias HaTorah (קריאת התורה). krias HaTorah But I'm
just saying by Megilla (מגילה) Megilla we don't rule this way.
But for whatever reason maybe Megilla (מגילה) Megilla is different you're saying?
Yeah, because...
because Megilla (מגילה) Megilla certainly the... is taken as a personal obligation,
whereas krias HaTorah (קריאת התורה) krias HaTorah is only a tzibur (ציבור)
tzibur obligation. I don't have a personal obligation if I'm home and
I didn't go to shul (שול) shul to read the Torah by
myself. I don't even have a personal obligation, so don't tell the...
the people say you shouldn't tell people this because then people won't
go to shul (שול), shul but I don't have a personal obligation
to go to shul (שול) shul and hear krias HaTorah (קריאת התורה).
krias HaTorah It's only an obligation on the community, right? So therefore
you can frame it in the way I did. Megilla (מגילה) Megilla
we start by framing it as a personal obligation, so what I
put out there is more of a chiddush (חידוש).
chiddush Yes, that's true of as a minyan (מניין) minyan as a
whole, isn't it?
Correct. That I don't... yeah.
So far, unless I missed it, women are not prohibited from reading.
Not only not prohibited, there is... I mean, right? There's... you know,
it... exclude... they are... there is nothing that gives them any different
status, right? The only people excluded here were cheiresh (חרש), cheiresh shoteh
(שוטה), shoteh and katan (קטן). katan And, you know, the mishna (משנה),
mishna first mishna (משנה) mishna in Arachin (ערכין) Arachin is hakol hayavin
(הכל חייבין), hakol hayavin hakol asuyim nashim (הכל עשויין נשים) hakol asuyim
nashim the Gemara (גמרא) Gemara says. All the simple sense of it
is that not only are women obligated, which everybody acknowledges, but that
at the same level of obligation as men and can read for
men. It's only because of a Tosefta (תוספתא), Tosefta the Bahag (בה"ג),
Bahag and whatever, this strand enters into Ashkenazic (אשכנזי) Ashkenazic thought that
introduced an idea that maybe women are obligated but at a different
level. But certainly nothing in the Gemara (גמרא) Gemara indicates that. Okay,
let's take a look at the next mishna (משנה). mishna Ein korin
es haMegilla (אין קורין את המגילה), ein korin es haMegilla velo malin
(ולא מלין), velo malin velo tovilin (ולא טובלין), velo tovilin velo mazin
(ולא מזין), velo mazin vechein shomeres yom keged yom (וכן שומרת יום
כנגד יום), vechein shomeres yom keged yom lo tivol ad shetenetz hachama
(לא תטבול עד שתנץ החמה). lo tivol ad shetenetz hachama So now
that we're dealing... now we're getting really like into the concrete aspects
of the mitzva (מצווה). mitzva So we discussed how the reading is
done, we're discussing now... so that's the how. Then we did the
who, who is obligated? Now we're sort of at a little bit
I guess of the what, of the... well what we know. Anyway,
now we're at the when. So when is it done? So we...
it's done... it's a day. And in this context though we make
a much broader statement in this mishna (משנה) mishna and the next
mishna (משנה) mishna about day mitzvos (מצוות). mitzvos And the first point
we're making is implicitly everything we're listing here are day mitzvos (מצוות).
mitzvos So that's point number one that's being asserted. And point number
two, which is the greater emphasis at least of this mishna (משנה),
mishna is that a day mitzva (מצווה) mitzva should begin ad shetenetz
hachama (עד שתנץ החמה), ad shetenetz hachama after sunrise. Vechulan sheasaun (וכולן
שעשאן) vechulan sheasaun I'll get back and reread the list, but let's
just point... finish this point vechulan sheasaun misheala amud hashachar kasher (וכולן
שעשאן משעלה עמוד השחר כשר). vechulan sheasaun misheala amud hashachar kasher But
even though day mitzvos (מצוות) mitzvos begin at... should begin at sunrise,
if you did them from the time the morning star arose, it
is kasher (כשר). kasher The morning star is basically assumed to be
seventy-two minutes before... four mil (מיל) mil before sunrise. Okay, so and
we'll talk in a minute about what this idea is about a
לכתחילה lechatchila *lechatchila* time to start a day מצוה mitzva *mitzvah* and
a בדיעבד bedieved? *bedi'eved* time. So what are these מצוות mitzvos *mitzvos*?
Reading of the מגילה megila. *Megillah*, ברית מילה bris milah *bris milah*,
טבילה tevilah *tevilah*. Now I'll discuss טבילה tevilah *tevilah* in a minute.
הזאה haza'ah *hazah* is the sprinkling of the ashes of the פרה
אדומה parah adumah *parah adumah* for somebody who's טמא מת tamei meis,
*teme meit* and a שומרת יום כנגד יום shomeres yom k'neged yom,
*shomeres yom k'neged yom*, a woman who bled one or two days
not during her menstrual period, she has to wait one clean day,
one day of no bleed, and then she goes to the מקוה
mikvah, *mikvah*. So
and she goes to מקוה mikvah, *mikvah*. So if she saw some
blood on Sunday, so Monday she waits until she did not see
blood, and once some of Monday day has entered in and there
has
not been any blood, then she goes to the מקוה mikvah, *mikvah*
on that day. So that's the going in the daytime, that's שומרת
יום כנגד יום shomeres yom k'neged yom. *shomeres yom k'neged yom*. לא
תטבול עד שתנץ החמה *lo tivol ad she'tanetz hachamah*. She has to
wait till sunrise of the following day of Monday. What? That's right.
So the question is why is that different than the טבילה tevilah
*tevilah* we said before? Why is שומרת יום shomeres yom *shomeres yom*
being singled out? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to discuss
that. Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. מנלן menalan?
*minalan*, where is this coming from? דאמר קרא d'amar kra, *d'amar kra*,
the verse says, meaning מנלן *minalan* at least of the first מצוה
mitzvah *mitzvah* of the מגילה Megillah *Megillah*, והימים האלה נזכרים ונעשים *v'hayammim
ha'eleh nizkarim v'naasim*. These days are remembered and performed. So and we
discussed before the whole idea of זכירה *zichirah* of memory being the
ritual of reading of not just remembering in your mind, but and
it says הימים *hayammim*, ביום bayom. אין בלילה לא *bayom in v'layla
lo*, only in the day, not at night. It's so meaning the
first thing we're going to establish by all of these is that
they're day מצוות mitzvos *mitzvos*. Then we're going to establish the second
point of the issue of נץ החמה neitz hachamah *netz hachamah* and
עלות השחר Alos Hashachar, *alos hashachar*, how do you define day? But
the first thing we establish is it's a day מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לימא תהוי תיובתא דרבי יהושע בן
לוי *leima t'vei kiyufta d'rabi yehoshua ben levi*, let's say this is
the contradiction of Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi? דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי
*d'amar rabbi yehoshua ben levi*, חייב אדם לקרות את המגילה בלילה ולשנותה
ביום bayom. *chayav adam likros es hamigillah balayla v'lishnosa bayom*. A person
has to read the מגילה *Megillah* at night and repeat it during
the day. And here it only mentions the day obligation, it doesn't
mention the night. It sounds like there's no night obligation. So גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says כי תניא אדיום *ki tanya ad hayom*, no, when
the משנה mishnah *Mishnah* says that the day מצוה *mitzvah*, that the
מצוה *mitzvah* מגילה *Megillah* is in the day, starts from הנץ החמה
haneitz hachamah, *hanetz hachamah*, it means the day מצוה *mitzvah* of מגילה
*Megillah* is at the day, but it doesn't say it's talking about
when the day is marked. It doesn't talk about it's not there's
also a night מצוה *mitzvah* which it's not addressing. Now that's the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s answer, but I will say not only do like
modern academics, but even, you know, אחרונים *acharonim* have pointed out that
that is not historically correct that the משנה mishna. *Mishnah* also believed
in a nighttime מצוה *mitzvah* of reading. Already the פני יהושע *Pnei
Yehoshua* says, or no, maybe it's the שאגת אריה *Shagas Aryeh* says,
the משניות *mishnayos* and the tannaitic material have no knowledge of a
nighttime מצוה *mitzvah* of reading the מגילה *Megillah*. This is an idea
that was introduced by Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi and here they say
the point that I said before, which is that they call the
day reading a מצוה מדברי סופרים *mitzvah midivrei soferim* because it's based
on the verses of the מגילה *Megillah*, and the night מצוה *mitzvah*
a מצוה דרבנן *mitzvah d'rabanan*. And that actually again is significant because
people are so much more, you know, מקפיד *makpid* about the night
one and in practice, if you had to choose between going to
a night reading and a day reading, you should go to the
day reading. The day reading is the primary מצוה *mitzvah*. So the
reason the משנה mishna *Mishnah* doesn't mention it is not just because
it wasn't discussing it, it doesn't mention it because it doesn't know
of it. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* manages to reconcile it
and say no, we're talking about the day reading, we're not coming
to exclude a night reading. Okay. ולא מלין *v'lo malin*, ברית מילה
bris milah *bris milah* is only during the day, דכתיב d'chtiv, וביום
השמיני ימול *d'ksiv u'vayom hashmini yimal*, and on the eighth day he
shall do the מילה *milah*, which means right so there actually is
an interesting discussion if it's מילה שלא בזמנה *milah shelo bizmanah* is
night excluded? So this is minimally excluding the night of the eighth,
the night preceding the eighth, but because it only begins the day
of the eighth, whether it must be day if it's if it's
done later, that's actually discussed.
Yes. So the idea that the day מצוה *mitzvah* and the night
מצוה *mitzvah* for מגילה *Megillah* are different brings the possibility that maybe
the obligation and who can read might be different.
Right, so there are those Rabbi Weiss in an article that he
wrote in the Torah U'Madda journal or whatever, but basically there are
those who put out that even for people who want to be
concerned with the position that תוספות Tosfos. *Tosafos* introduces that women's obligation
is at a different level and so on, that maybe to limit
that type of a concern to the day מצוה *mitzvah*, but the
night מצוה *mitzvah*, where it's clearly anyway at a different level, so
and this concern is not פשט pshat *pshat* in the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* and so on, and maybe conceptually you can frame this issue
differently. So yes, there is that there is that idea that's put
out there, which works conveniently because as I said, because the night
one is the one that in practice if not in הלכה halacha
*halacha* everybody makes a much bigger deal about. So yes. Alright, moving
on. ולא מלין *v'lo malin*, דכתיב d'ksiv, וביום השמיני ימול *d'ksiv u'vayom
hashmini yimal*, ולא טובלין tovlin ולא מזין *v'lo tovlin v'lo mazin*. So
you do not do the טבילה tevilah *tevilah* and the הזאה *hazah*
for פרה אדומה parah adumah. *parah adumah*. I'm going to say something
about טבילה tevilah *tevilah* in a minute. Let's read the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. דכתיב d'ksiv, והזה
הטהור על הטמא *d'ksiv v'hizah hatahor al hatame*. The The one who
is טהור shall sprinkle the ashes on the one who is טמא
tamei ביום השביעי beyom hashvi'i on the day of the seventh, so
not earlier, it has to be the day of the seventh. איתקש
טבילה להזאה itkash tevilah le'haza'ah and the טבילה tevilah that you're טובל
tovel in the process of being מיטהר mitaher from the פרה אדומה
parah adumah, is connected to the sprinkling. Now what טבילה tevilah are
we talking about? So there is a long תוספות. Tosfos And תוספות
Tosfos basically demonstrates that the גמרא Gemara. understands that actually there are
two טבילות tevilot that take place in the context of sprinkling the
ashes of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah One is you do a
טבילה tevilah, prior to the sprinkling to prepare you, you know, for
the act of sprinkling. That's not really clear in the verses. And
then the other is you do a טבילה tevilah. after the sprinkling,
which is clear in the verses that that is what is done.
So which one are we saying has to be done during the
day? So תוספות Tosfos says well, it would seem that we're saying
that because we say טובלין ומזין tovlin u'mazin that we're talking about
the טבילה tevilah, prior to the sprinkling has to be the day.
The only problem is that evidence from other גמרות Gemoras show that
the טבילה tevilah, prior to the הזאה could be at night. So
that doesn't work. So maybe we're talking about the טבילה tevilah after
the sprinkling. It says but the problem is, like we just said
a minute ago relating to the issue of the ברית מילה and
there it was debated but here it's clear, after the sprinkling was
done in the day, when we say טבילה, tevilah let's say anybody
who does a טבילה. tevilah A זב zav does a טבילה, a
זבה zavah does a טבילה, we say it has to be in
the day of the seventh. That's only the first time, the earliest
time you could do it is day of the seventh and not
the night before. But if you wanted to do it later, you
could do a טבילה the following night, right? The טבילה in the
day only is the first time you can do it is the
daytime but afterwards you can do it in the night. So תוספות
Tosfos says the same about sprinkling of the ashes of the פרה
אדומה, parah adumah. right? If I sprinkle the ashes of the פרה
אדומה on you, right, so then and that has to be daytime
because we already said that has to be day. If we're talking
about the טבילה after, that doesn't have to be day, that can
be now it has to come after, so it's already going to
be day of the seventh and it can actually be at night
so it doesn't make any sense to say it has to be
day. So תוספות Tosfos actually says and this is very creative that
טובלין here does not mean you go into the מקוה, mikvah, it
means the immersion of the hyssop into the waters of the פרה
אדומה. And he actually brings evidence that says that if you do
the dipping at night and the sprinkling at the day, it's not
good. That you actually have to dip it in the water in
the day and then do the sprinkling.
I'm sorry, how would that work? Dipping at night and sprinkling during
the day?
Right before עמוד השחר, amud hashachar, it's one minute before עמוד השחר
amud hashachar I dip it and then it's עמוד השחר amud hashachar
and then I sprinkle. Okay, so that's how תוספות Tosafos reads it.
So anyway, alright, which gets us then to the issue of שומרת
יום shomeres yom because the actual הלכה halacha is that anytime that
the Torah does speak about being טובל tovel in the you know,
like waiting and being טובל tovel seven days for a זב zav
or a זבה zavah and then being טובל tovel or and so
on you know, that that earliest time, the one exception is a
נדה. niddah. A נדה niddah waits seven days from the onset and
then she is
טובלת, tovelet, you know at the night that at the end of
a full seven days. But normally if there's a period of like
seven day clean days like by a זב zav and a זבה,
zavah, you know or מצורע metzora there's this process and then after
a long process of a cleansing type of a process there's a
going to the מקוה, mikvah, right? Then that is that takes place
on the day of the seven and not the night before. Okay,
so that is you know that's the issue of ביום. So the
question is then so that's true really by anybody who goes to
the מקוה, mikvah but once it's once the day of the seven
if you do it late you can do it in the night
time. It's just the earliest time is the day of the seven
not the night of the seven. So the question becomes why the
משנה mishna singles out שומרת יום shomeres yom? since this is really
true about anybody who goes to the מקוה, mikvah. you go in
the first thing in the day. Why single out שומרת יום? shomeres
yom, Or you're allowed to go as early as the day but
no as the beginning of the day but no earlier. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. וכן שומרת יום כנגד יום לא תטבול
עד שתצא החמה. v'chen shomeres yom kineged yom lo titbol ad she'tetzait
hachamah. פשיטא pshita obviously, מאי שנא שומרת יום כנגד יום מכל חייבי
טבילות. mai shena shomeres yom kineged yom mi'kol chayavei tevilos. All people
who have to
go to the מקוה, mikvah, right? The first if you have to
wait a day then you can't do it at night you have
to wait till the beginning of the day. Again, as I say
once the day begins you can do it following that at night
as well but if you had to wait a day then the
first thing you can do it is in the morning not earlier.
So why is that different from anybody else? איצטריך. itzrich. No, you
need to tell me this. סלקא דעתך אמינא salika da'atach amina I
would have thought to say תהוי כראייה ראשונה של זב. tehavei k're'iyah
rishonah shel zav. That a woman who bleeds one day not during
her cycle should be like a man who has a penile emission,
a זב, zav, which is not semen, and that so that's a
זב zav and a זבה zavah they're in somewhat of a similar
category and the first few times you
know they're not yet in the full status so I would have
made a comparison. ראייה ראשונה של זב איתקש לבעל קרי re'iyah rishonah
shel zav itkash l'ba'al keri and we know that a man who
is a זב zav if it's only one time it's the same
status as a בעל קרי ba'al keri until it's twice. ראייה ראשונה
של זב דכתיב re'iyah rishonah shel zav dechtiv in it says וזאת
תורת הזב אשר תצא ממנו שכבת זרע. zos toras hazav asher taitzai
mimenu shichvas zera.
This is the rule of the one man with flow and into
what comes from him a seminal emission.
So those are halachically linked and that actually is true that after
somebody, a man has had one type of a זב, zav, of
a flow, he has the status of a בעל קרי. ba'al keri.
So I would have said מה בעל קרי טובל ביום, ma ba'al
keri tovel b'yom, so the same way that the בעל קרי ba'al
keri goes to the מקוה mikvah the day he sees, right, this
is a case that you don't wait to go. There are some
times you have to wait a day, but sometimes like if you
touch a dead carcass or a man was a בעל קרי, ba'al
keri, you go the day that this happened. So in this case,
so מה בעל קרי טובל ביום, האי נמי לטבול ביומיה, ma ba'al
keri tovel b'yom, hai nami litvol b'yomei, so
therefore this one also can be—this one, meaning a זב, zav, could
be טובל tovel the same day. And if a זב zav could
be טובל tovel the same day, maybe a זבה zavah could be
טובל tovel the same day that she saw her first spot of
blood. והא ביממא לא מצי טבלה, veha b'imama lo matzi tavlah, but
we know that a זבה zavah cannot go the very day that
she saw the spot of blood, דכתיב, d'ksiv, because the verse says,
כל ימי זובה כמשכב נדתה יהיה לה. kol yemei zovah k'mishkav niddasah
yihiyeh lah. All the days of her flow, like the seat of
a נדה, niddah, of a menstrual woman, shall be for her. So
now what does that prove? So all it proves is this word
of יהיה לה, yihiyeh lah, shall be for her, from which the
Rabbis learn this concept of שומרת יום כנגד יום, shomeres yom k'neged
yom, which means that if a woman bleeds—again, I'll say this
again—the הלכה is like this: a woman who is not during her
menstrual cycle, if she sees three days in a row blood, she's
considered a זבה גדולה zavah gedolah and she needs to wait שבעה
נקיים, shiva nekiyim, seven clean days, and that's what we sort of
pattern our current laws of נדה niddah on, that idea of a
שבעה נקיים shiva nekiyim period. But if she only bleeds one or
two days not during her menstrual period, then she waits one day
without seeing any blood, and then she goes to the מקוה. mikvah
And that's what we're talking about, שומרת יום shomeres yom, כנגד יום.
yom. She observes a day opposite the day that she bled. Even
if she bleeds two days, she only has to observe one day.
And in that one day that she's not seeing anything, she goes
to the מקוה, mikvah she can go even early in the morning,
and she's טהורה. tehorah. So but it's—and we learn that from the
word יהיה. yihiyeh. יהיה yihiyeh shall be, we learn that equal to
the fact that she saw blood on a day, יהיה yihiyeh she
has to observe an equal, a corresponding day of טהרה. taharah. So
the basic פשט pshat, of this being that a זבה zavah cannot,
unlike a זב zav and a בעל קרי, ba'al keri, a זבה
zavah cannot go to the מקוה mikvah on the day that it
occurred. She has to wait till the next day. Okay, so we
learned that you have to wait till the next day, but there's
still something pulling us to want to do it the same day
because of this comparison to a זב zav and a בעל קרי.
ba'al keri. So therefore I might have been inclined to say בלילה
מי איכא דעביד מקצת שימור וטבלה, balailah mi ika de'avid miktzas shimur
v'tavlah, why not say the observing, שומרת יום, Yom. that she's not
bleeding, why not say that that happens at the beginning of the
night? Why do you have to wait till the next morning? So
she saw some blood Sunday day, why not say, okay, we get
this idea that
she—like logically she should have been able to go to the מקוה
mikvah on Sunday, just like a בעל קרי ba'al keri and a
זב zav the first day, but the Torah says she has to
observe a period of being clean, of not bleeding. Why not say
the period of not bleeding is a little bit of Sunday night
and go to the מקוה mikvah Sunday night וטבלה? v'tavlah? So she's
not somebody that fundamentally, it's not like one of these ideas like
a full זב zav or like, you know, somebody who touched a
dead body that has an idea of a seven-day period. Basically the
idea is she should be able to go right away, but she
has to observe a small amount of time that she's not bleeding.
So why do you have to wait till the daytime? Let her
do it at night and go at night. So I might have
thought that as opposed to other people, she should be able to
go at night and not have to wait till the day. קמשמע
לן, kamashma lan, so it's teaching us, כיון דבעיא ספירה, keivan d'ba'aya
sfirah, since the Torah says וספרה לה v'safrah lah by a זבה
zavah that she has to count seven full days and this is
somewhat similar to a זבה, zavah, she's like one or two days,
so there's an idea of counting וספירה ביממא היא, u'sfirah b'imama hi,
to say designate that there was a clean day, not just that
there was a period that she didn't bleed, but a clean day,
that has to be in the daytime for it to count as
a clean day. Okay, so this is again, it's a little confusing,
but the idea is there are people—a—you can
go—let's not misunderstand. You can go to the מקוה mikvah. at night.
First of all, nowadays women always go to the מקוה mikvah. at
night, right? And the Torah נדה niddah will go to the מקוה
mikvah. at night. The issue is that when there's a period of
like clean days that the Torah
designates—זב, zav, זבה, zavah, מצורע, metzora, טמא מת, and so on—that that
period, right, let's say it's normally a seven-day period, that period ends
on day seven. And this, by the way, the important principle here
that I didn't say explicitly is like the idea of like seven—like
on the seventh day of אבילות, aveilus, the idea of מקצת היום
ככולו. miktzas hayom k'kulo. Right? So it's a seven-day period, the חידוש
chiddush here is is that it's a seven-day period but you don't
have to wait till the end of seven days. At the beginning
of the seventh day, you can already go to the מקוה. mikvah,
Okay? But just like אבילות, aveilus, somebody doesn't get up from אבילות
aveilus the night before, even though it's halachically the seventh day, you
have to wait till the morning of the seventh day. So here
too, you wait till the morning of the seventh day and go
to the מקוה. That's the principle. So it has to wait till
the morning, okay? So the גמרא Gemara says that is generally the
principle. If we have a seven-day, it has to go into the
daytime of the seventh day to count. And even שומרת יום Yom,
כנגד יום, which isn't the idea of seven days, it's just an
idea of a שמירה shmirah period, there is an idea of counting
one day and therefore it has to go into the daytime of
the next day before going to the מקוה. Okay, but once that
period has arrived, the day of the seventh day or the day
of the following day for a שומרת יום, then if you postponed
it, you could certainly go the following night. Okay, so that's the
idea of these things being in the day. Yes?
How do we where do we get the that it can't be
told? Why wouldn't we just say that okay, it's compared to all
these other cases?
Because as I'm telling you, all these other cases there's a period
of טהרה. taharah. Like the נדה niddah she could be bleeding all
seven days. All these other cases, it's seven clean days. So you
have to fill the seven clean days and the the idea is
the beginning of the seventh counts like the full seven.
For לא פלוג, lo plug, right? So just like other people,
it's not לא פלוג, lo plug, it's a completely different process. Okay,
וכולן שעשו משעלה עמוד השחר כשר. V'chulan she'asu mishe'alah amud hashachar kasher.
And all of them if you did them now we get so
these are idea that these are daytime things. Now we get to
the idea of defining the day. So it should start at הנץ
החמה, haneitz hachamah. but if you did it from the morning star,
you were יוצא. yotzei. So מנא הני מילי, mana hani mili, where
do you get this from? אמר רבא דאמר קרא, Amar Rava de'amar
kra, the verse says ויקרא אלהים לאור יום, Vayikra Elokim la'ohr yom,
God called the light day. So the so we're saying now here's
the דרשה, drasha, which one might say is not the פשט, but
here's the דרשה, drasha, למאיר
ובא קראו יום. L'me'ir u'va k'rao yom. So when it was beginning
to give light, he called that period day. So not only not
the light, first of all, which is a funny idea, right? Light
isn't called day, light is called light. What does it mean God
called light day? So it means he means the period of light.
But the גמרא Gemara is reading it, what does it mean the
period of light? When it begins to become light, he called that
period day. So when does it begin to become light? Before sunrise.
It begins to become light at עמוד השחר. amud hashachar. So that
already is called day. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא מעתה, ela
me'ata, if you read it that way, ולחשך קרא לילה, v'lachoshech kara
lailah, it says he called the darkness night. So darkness isn't night,
it means the period of darkness is night, and we'll read it
as למחשיך ובא קרא לילה, l'machshich u'va kara lailah, as it is
getting dark, he called it night. So if you want to read
as it's getting light it's considered day, let's say as it's getting
dark it's considered night. But that's not true, that's dusk. הא קיימא
לן, Ha kaima lan, but we hold, דצאת הכוכבים לאו לילה הוא,
d'tzeis hakochavim lav lailah hu,
until the stars come out it's not night. So אלא אמר רבי
זירא מהכא, ela amar Rabbi Zeira meihacha, so Rabbi Zeira says from
here. So you're right, you can't get it from there because then
you wouldn't have the parallel. But here, and again interestingly quoting a
verse in נחמיה, Nechemia, which gets us back to בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash and the בנין בית המקדש, binyan Beis Hamikdash, which is exactly
the context of this whole
מסכתא. masechta. ואנחנו עושים במלאכה, V'anachnu osim bamalacha, we were doing the
work of building the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, וחציים מחזיקים ברמחים, v'chetziyam
machzikim baramachim, and half of the people were bearing like spears, they
were the guards, מעלות השחר עד צאת הכוכבים, me'alos hashachar ad tzeis
hakochavim, from the morning star until the stars came out. ואומר, V'omer,
and the verse says והיו לנו הלילה למשמר והיום מלאכה, v'hayu lanu
halailah l'mishmar v'hayom malacha, the nighttime was the time of guarding and
the daytime was the time of working. So you see it says
that they were working from עלות alos till צאת tzeis and it
says they were working in the day. So that defines day. So
מאי ואומר, mai v'omer, why do you need the second verse? It
already says from the עלות alos till צאת. tzeis. וכי תימא, V'chi
teima, you might have said משעלה עמוד השחר לאו יממא הוא, mishe'alah
amud hashachar lav yimama hu, no, maybe they were working from עלות
alos but it doesn't mean that that was day, maybe that was
even before daybreak. ומכי ערבה שמשא ליליא, U'michi arvah shimsha leilya, and
maybe as soon as the sun set it was already night and
they were just working late till צאת. tzeis. How do we know
that the day the time they were working met was defined as
daytime? Maybe they were starting early and ending late. דאינון מקדמי ומחשכי,
De'inun makdimi u'machshichi, they would start early and end late. תא שמע,
Ta shma, come here's the verse, והיו לנו הלילה למשמר והיום מלאכה,
v'hayu lanu halailah l'mishmar v'hayom malacha, it says that they worked during
the day. So you see the period of עלות alos till צאת
tzeis is defined as the day. Now, this doesn't exactly answer why
לכתחילה lechatchila you should wait till הנץ החמה. haneitz hachamah, By the
way, everybody says it wrong, they say נץ החמה as if the
hey was the הי הידיעה, hey hayedia, the הנץ החמה, haneitz hachamah,
but it's הנץ, haneitz, הנץ החמה, haneitz hachamah? the hey is the
הטיפי"ו, hitfio, it's about anyway it's part of the verb.
הניצו הרמונים, Heinitzu harimonim, good example. Anyway, so anyway, why לכתחילה lechatchila
are you supposed to wait to הנץ החמה? Hanetz Hachama, Why is
it why is עמוד השחר amud hashachar only בדיעבד? b'diavad So רש"י
Rashi says, well, because everybody knows when sunrise is, so that's a
good clear time. If you say you can do it from עמוד
השחר, amud hashachar, you know, it's cloudy, if you're shining, you won't
know, people will say it too early, it's not very easy to
identify and therefore it's just like a rabbinic safeguard. That's the way
what?
משום הרחק מן העבירה? mishum harchaik min ha'aveirah?
No, whatever, rabbinic safeguard. That's what רש"י Rashi says. But it's possible
to say something at a more conceptual level and this is what
רב סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik says, and we get to this issue here
about למאיר ובא. l'me'ir u'va. למחשכו בא le'machshicho ba and so on,
which is, you know, that really there were like these periods, right?
You have sunrise,
right? And then you have the morning star. I don't know why
I'm looking at you anyway, I'm doing it right
to left. It's very picturesque. I know, anyway I'm not the best
with gestures. Sunrise, and you have the morning star, right, which is
עלות השחר, Alos Hashachar
right? Then you have sunset
and צאת. Tzet. Now we have terms for these middle periods, right?
Right? This is dusk,
right? What's this period before it's the morning star? Do we have
a term for that? First light? Dawn, I guess.
The point at which
the... What? Dawn is a point not a period.
Alright, so anyway, so this but okay, but this is somewhat parallel,
maybe we don't have a term for it, but this is somewhat
parallel. So the question is, right, what's day and what's night? Like,
what do you do if this these are like gray, they literally
are somewhat gray. Okay, these are like gray, right? This and the
rest is like black and white, right? That's black and this is
white. So this is clearly day. What do you do with these
periods that are somewhere between, like, the twilight zone, right, somewhere between
day and night? That's the question. So the so so you know,
so what so that's the idea of למאי אור בא. Le'mai or
ba. What do you do when it's becoming light and it's not
yet light? Or למחשכו בא, le'machshicho ba, it's getting dark, but it's
not yet fully dark. What is the halachic status of these gray
zones? So the so the idea is that from עלות השחר Alos
Hashachar. till הנץ החמה, haneitz hachamah the halachic status is that this
is like, this is the way רב Rav סולובייצ'יק Soloveitchik says, this
is like בדיעבד b'diavad יום. The halachic status is that it really
is day, but it's not yet like fully day, but it's technically
bottom line it is day, but you know not not fully. So
therefore don't לכתחילה read at this point because בדיעבד b'diavad this isn't
like fully day, full day only begins here. But it is partial
day. Okay, and therefore because it is partial day בדיעבד b'diavad you're
יוצא. yotzeh. Now, what's the story from sunset until צאת? Tzet? Dusk,
what do we call that halachically? בין השמשות. Bein Hashmashot. What do
we call this period? בין השמשות. Bein Hashmashot. What's the status if
you do something בין השמשות? Bein Hashmashot? It's a ספק, safek, right?
It's right, בין השמשות Bein Hashmashot is a ספק, safek, right? So
if you did it so here the way we deal with the
gray is we say בדיעבד b'diavad it's day. Here the way we
deal with the gray is halachically we give it a status of
being a period of doubt. So some people understand that the reason
this is a ספק, safek, בין השמשות, Bein Hashmashot, is we don't
know when צאת הכוכבים Tzet Hakochavim occurred during that time. But the
רב Rav said it's not like we don't know. It's like we're
trying to figure out what status do we give the period between
sunset and צאת? Tzet? What do we give that period? And that
has a halachic status of being a mix. If you would, doubtful
because really this is a mix of day and night. Okay, now
you can understand so they say, well, that's not parallel, which is
sort of the issue the גמרא Gemara is saying, right? Why don't
we say that if this is בדיעבד b'diavad day, this is בדיעבד
b'diavad? night, right? Why one do we define as a mix and
the other we define as a mix but no good even בדיעבד?
b'diavad Well, it's no, it's a mix which is a ספק בדיעבד.
safek b'diavad. So a period which is both day and night or
a mixture of day and night or quasi day and night is
a ספק. safek. And that's why things done בין השמשות Bein Hashmashot
have a status of ספק, safek, ספק יום ספק לילה. safek yom
safek lyla. So I think that the reason that it's not fully
parallel is as the day is growing lighter, למאי אור בא, Le'mai
or ba, you understand that there's a idea of sort of seeing
this as the beginning of day. Like it's getting lighter and lighter
and lighter although it's still darkness, it's still dark out there, you
would see that בדיעבד bedieved it's day because the light is growing.
Of course, you know, you could have said the same here, it's
getting dark so it's the beginning of night, but again, I think
it's just the human desire towards light. So even though it's getting
dark we're like hanging on to the sort of remnants of the
light that are still there, we're not ready to give up the
day yet, right?
And therefore this period is doesn't get tipped in either direction, it
remains halachically like a ספק. safek. Okay, so that's just I think
an important way of sort of thinking about these periods that we're
dealing with.
Yes?
It's interesting what you're saying about your graphics there because
the
middle
is
the
one about the sun and the two extremes is all about stars.
So in this middle section area
the question is is the sun yet doing its work? I'm sorry,
between sunrise and
עלות השחר. Right? And the question is when is the sun
shining? Right? When has the sun made its day?
Yeah.
Charlie?
Yeah, the verses from Nehemiah
are simply describing the practicality of when they could build the walls
of ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. The proof is not that they worked from עמוד השחר Amud
HaShachar to צאת Tzeis but that they labeled it יום. That's the
proof. That's why the גמרא Gemara. said we needed the extra verse.
If they hadn't labeled it יום, it wouldn't have proved anything. Yes,
Michael.
So according to at least the way I understand this, if it's
the wrong thing I'm okay, but according to רש״י Rashi it's more
of like we might not know, but if we for sure knew
it was a nice clear day and then then it should really
be okay.
Right, exactly, right, exactly. All right, so now let's take a look
at the next משנה. mishnah So that's got us to the definition
of when day begins and what sort of incidentally identifying which are
some things that are day מצוות mitzvos that require day. The point
of this משנה mishnah not radically different, but the point of this
משנה is to identify a list of things that are day מצוות
again and if you want to also point out not the beginning
but the fact that they can begin as early as עמוד השחר
Amud HaShachar but should begin at הנץ haneitz החמה but to point
out the end that they can go the entire day till the
end of the day. Okay, so let's take a look. כל היום
Kol hayom the entirety of the day כשר לקריאת המגילה kasher likrias
hamigila fit for the reading of the מגילה. So yes, it's a
day מצוה begins at
הנץ בדיעבד bedieved at עמוד השחר Amud HaShachar but this point is
but can go all the way if you didn't do it at
the beginning can go the whole day. ולקריאת ההלל Ulekrias haHallel although
הלל Hallel is normally said at שחרית Shacharis if somehow you forgot
it was ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh or whatever you skipped it you
can say הלל Hallel later in the day. ולתקיעת שופר Uletkias shofar
same point although we do תקיעת שופר tkias shofar towards the beginning
you can do it technically the whole day. ונטילת לולב Unetilas lulav
taking the לולב lulav ולתפילת מוספין ulitefilas Musafin the prayer of מוסף
Musaf ולמוספין ulimusafin and actually bringing a קרבן מוסף. korban Musaf. What?
Yeah ולוידוי הפרים ulividuy haparim could have right but שחרית Shacharis is
not the whole day מנחה Mincha is not the whole day.
No it has chosen items that are קרבנות korbanos or תפילות tefillos
as we're bringing until המוספין והמוספין. haMusafin vehaMusafin.
Okay well the גמרא Gemara is going to say they were basically
the same point. But it's a חידוש chiddush right? Because we know
other aspects of our דאווענינג davening שחרית Shacharis is only in the
morning מנחה Mincha is only in the afternoon מוסף Musaf is the
whole day. ולוידוי הפרים Ulividuy haparim the the וידוי viduy the confession
done over various cows that are brought like פר העלם דבר של
ציבור par he'elam davar shel tzibur and other types of times that
oxen are brought and there's a special וידוי viduy that's
for
the blood to be sprinkled inside the קודש Kodesh and there's a
וידוי viduy that's done. ולוידוי מעשר Ulividuy ma'aser the confession done once
a person brings the מעשר ma'aser after it's been sort of stored
up in the house. ולוידוי יום הכיפורים Ulividuy Yom HaKippurim and the
וידוי viduy done on יום כיפור Yom Kippur presumably not talking about
the וידוי viduy we say in שחרית Shacharis but the וידוי viduy
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol does on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
What?
over the שעיר sa'ir and over the פר par over the animal.
So you can do it at the end of the day like
hours after you brought it?
It doesn't really matter? No no. You can bring it later in
the day. You have to do it while the animal's still alive.
It's not talking about what other things have to be in place.
Okay? You can't bring the מוסף Musaf for example after the תמיד
של בין הערביים Tamid shel bein ha'arbayim is brought. Okay but it's
talking about the the time of day per se does not limit
you.
And it doesn't really mean וידוי viduy for bringing the פר. par.
That too. We'll talk about it. Fine. We'll see it in the
גמרא. Gemara Okay
ולסמיכה ולשחיטה ulisemicha ulishchita now really all acts of עבודה avoda in
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash both require day but can take place
anytime in the day. Whether it's doing סמיכה semicha on the קרבנות
korbanos putting the hands on the קרבן, korban, שחיטה shchita the קרבן,
korban, תנופה tnufa the waving that's done with various קרבנות, korbanos, ולהגשה
ulhagasha by a מנחה Mincha touching the מנחה Mincha to the מזבח
mizbeach is done as a part of the עבודה, avoda, ולקמיצה uliktmiza
taking the handbreadth from the מנחה, Mincha, ולהקטרה ulhaktara burning the handbreadth,
ולמליקה ulmelika you know severing the neck of a bird sacrifice, ולקבלה
ulkabala catching the blood of a of a of a mammal cow
or the sheep, ולהזיה ulhazaya sprinkling the blood, ולהשקיית סוטה ulhashkayas sotah
the having the to do the ritual of the סוטה sotah water,
ולעריפת העגלה ula'rifas ha'agla breaking עגלה agla thank you עגלה egla something
else breaking the neck of the calf that's done with the you
don't know who the murderer is, ולטהרת המצורע ultaharas hametzora cleansing the
מצורע metzora the whole thing about the birds and the sprinkling and
all of that. כל אלו Kol elu all of those are day
מצוות and could be done anytime in the day or day rituals.
כל הלילה כשר לקצירת העומר ולהקטר חלבים ואיברים. Kol halaila kasher liktziras
ha'omer ulehakter chalavim ve'eivarim. And here are two nighttime rituals that can
be done anytime at night and they're nighttime rituals. Two points being
made. Number one: the cutting of the grain for the עומר omer
and number two: the burning of the fats that were not finished
burning the day before. Now the burning of the fats actually doesn't
have to wait till night, begins the day before but can proceed
continue through the night and go the entire night. זה הכלל Ze
haklal this is the principle. דבר שמצותו ביום כשר כל היום. Davar
shemitzvaso bayom kasher kol hayom. Something that can be done in the
day can be done the whole day. דבר שמצותו בלילה כשר כל
הלילה. Davar shemitzvaso balaila kasher kol halaila. Something that can be done
at night can be done the whole night. Again it's a pretty
principle זה הכלל ze haklal because I could tell you other things
that are מצוותן ביום mitzvasan bayom like you know how about שחרית?
Shacharis? Right? I mean as opposed to מוסף Musaf not everything is
true could be done the whole day and like calling
הקטרת חלבים haktaras chalavim מצוותו בלילה mitzvaso balaila what? תפילין Tefillin can
be. Right.
I'm just what?
That's also that's all. Correct. So, you know, right. And you know,
and again, calling like הקטרת חלבים haktaras chalavim מצותו בלילה mitzvato balaila
when it all begins the day before, it's an interesting type of
a זה כלל. zeh klal. But the point is as a general
rule, things although we tend to do certain things in the morning,
you know, ברית מילה other types of things, most of the general
rule is these things really are good the whole day. And things
that are can be done at night, generally can be done the
whole night. מנלן? Where do you know this from? דאמר קרא, the
verse says, so again, where do you know the מגילה part from?
The verse says הימים האלו נזכרים ונעשים. Hayamim ha'eileh nizkarim vena'asim.
So again, just tells us ימים, yamim, days, and presumably no reason
to limit it to specific hours in the day. לקריאת הלל, likrias
hallel, דכתיב, d'ksiv, ממזרח שמש עד מבואו. mimizrach shemesh ad mevo'o. And
we had that before when we were discussing the whole idea of
הלל, Hallel, you might remember, about doing it כסדרן kesidran when we
quoted the same verse. So from sunrise to sunset, what better a
proof do you need that's the whole day. רב יוסף אומר, Rav
Yosef omer, זה היום עשה ה'. zeh hayom asa Hashem. So this
is the day, the whole day. ונטילת לולב, untilas lulav, דכתיב, d'ksiv,
ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון. ulakachtem lachem bayom harishon. Again, day, no limit.
ולתקיעת שופר, ultkias shofar, דכתיב, d'ksiv, יום תרועה יהיה לכם, yom teruah
yihiyeh lachem, a day of blast. ולמוספין, ul'musafin, דכתיב, d'ksiv, דבר יום
ביומו. d'var yom biyomo. It's a thing in its day, okay, and
no particular limits to it. ולתפילת מוספין, ultfillas musafin, כמוספין שוו רבנן,
k'musafin shavei rabanan, because the prayer parallels the sacrifice. ולוידוי פרים, ul'vidui
parim, the confession done over the various times when you would bring
a special like פר, par, פר העלם דבר של ציבור, par he'elam
davar shel tzibur, פר כהן גדול. par Kohen Gadol. So those cases
normally when it's like a communal type of a sacrifice, ויליף veyalif
כפרה כפרה מיום הכיפורים. kapara kapara miYom HaKippurim. You learn up the
word atoning from יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. דתניא d'tanya לגבי יום הכיפורים,
lgabei Yom HaKippurim,
וכפר בעדו ובעד ביתו. vechiper ba'ado uva'ad beiso. The כהן Kohen will
make an atonement for himself and his household. בכפרת דברים הכתוב מדבר.
bekaparas devarim haksav medaber. It's talking about an atonement of words, about
a recitation of a וידוי. vidui. וכפרה ביומם היא, vekapara beyomam hi,
and we know that takes place in the day. דכתיב, d'ksiv, ביום
הזה יכפר עליכם, bayom hazeh yechaper aleichem, on this day. So you
don't make, you can't like do the confession the night before. Again,
some of this is pretty obvious since all the other aspects of
the sacrifice have to be in the day which we're about to
see. Okay, so that's about the idea of the confession. I think
it skips וידוי מעשר, vidui ma'aser, no, and the confession of מעשר,
ma'aser, דכתיב, d'ksiv, ואמרת לפני ה' אלהיך. ve'amarta lifnei Hashem Elokecha. This
is after three years you've let your מעשר ma'aser gather up, then
you sort of bring it all out and you distribute it and
you make this confession. בערתי הקדש מן הבית, bi'arti hakodesh min habayis,
I have distributed or removed the holy thing from the house. וסמיך
ליה, usmich lei, היום הזה ה' אלהיך מצוך. hayom hazeh Hashem Elokecha
m'tzavecha. This day God commands you. So that declaration has to be
in the day. So it's telling you number one it has to
be in the day, but it could be the whole day. ולסמיכה
ולשחיטה, ulismi'cha ulish'chita, to the placing of the hands and the slaughtering
of the קרבנות, korbanos, דכתיב, d'ksiv, וסמך ושחט, v'samach v'shachat, you should
place hands
and slaughter. וכתיב בשחיטה, u'ksiv bish'chita, ביום זבחכם, bayom zivchachem, on the
day of your slaughtering. ולתנופה, ultnufa, the waving, דכתיב, ביום הניפכם את
העומר, bayom hanifchem es ha'omer, the day you wave the עומר. Omer.
ולהגשה, ul'hagasha, דאתקש לתנופה, de'itkash litnufa, the bringing of the sacrifice to
the altar is connected to the waving. דכתיב, ולקח הכהן מיד האשה
את מנחת הקנאת velakach hakohen miyad ha'isha es minchas hakenos by the
סוטה, Sotah, והניף vehinif and he waves it and והקריב vehikriv and
he brings her close. והקריב vehikriv is understood this ritual of touching
it to the altar and it's juxtaposed to the תנופה. tnufa. We
learned that the תנופה tnufa is the day, so the act of
touching it to the altar is also in the day. ולמליקה ולקמיצה
ולהקטרה ולהזיה, ulmelika ul'kmitza ul'haktara ul'hazaya, all these other things: the severing
of the head of the bird, the taking of the handful, the
offering of it, the sprinkling, דכתיב, ביום צותו את בני ישראל להקריב
את קרבניהם, beyom tzovoso es Bnei Yisrael l'hakriv es korbaneihem, the day
He commanded בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael to bring their sacrifice. All things
of the sacrifice have to be in the day.
Of course, once
you got to that part, who needed everything that came before? Just
tell us everything about the sacrifice has to be in the day.
So it's quite possible it could have just had that פסוק. pasuk.
רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot try to have reasons why maybe I
would have needed some of those earlier פסוקים, pesukim, why maybe I
couldn't have included everything in this umbrella statement. But anyway, all things
of sacrifice are in the day. ולהשקאת סוטה, ul'hashkas Sotah, the סוטה
Sotah water, having the woman drink the
water, אתיא תורה תורה, asya torah torah, connection of the word תורה.
torah. דכתיב הכא, d'ksiv hacha, ועשה לה הכהן את כל התורה הזאת,
ve'asa lah hakohen es kol hatorah hazos, the כהן Kohen should do
all of this process. וכתיב התם, u'ksiv hasam, על פי התורה אשר
יורוך ועל המשפט אשר יאמרו לך תעשה al pi hatorah asher yorucha
v'al hamishpat asher yomru lecha ta'aseh by the idea of the בית
דין. Beis Din. And it says מה משפט ביום, mah mishpat bayom,
so the same way judgment occurs in the daytime. And רש"י Rashi
quotes if you look at רש"י Rashi gives you the פסוק, pasuk,
דכתיב והיה ביום הנחילו את בניו, d'ksiv v'haya beyom han'chilo es banav,
by a פסוק pasuk about bequeathing. So bequeathing doesn't seem like it's
a court case, it's a person who's bequeathing something. But the תורה
Torah basically, the גמרא basically learns that that's also that the whole
laws of bequest and of inheritance are considered a part of like
משפט mishpat and judgment. So anyway through that linking we get the
idea that judgment occurs during the day, the legal system works in
the day. So מה משפט ביום אף כאן ביום, mah mishpat bayom
af kan bayom, therefore the סוטה Sotah as well. I just say
one thing, we're not learning סוטה Sotah now, we won't learn it
for a while, but this idea of connecting it and therefore it's
the daytime based on this idea of משפט mishpat might just be
okay, it's just an arbitrary connection like, you know, we have a
word, we connect it. But it's interesting to note that You know,
the whole, the whole idea of סוטה sotah is obviously presents certain
challenges, but what one thing that is worth noting is that the
way the rabbis, maybe some similar a little bit to the whole
ערי מקלט arei miklat thing that we've read recently, you know, take,
where the Torah is already doing that, you take something that's more
in the hands of, like, not about a legal procedure and more
tries to bring it under the the control of a legal system.
So where a סוטה sotah in the Torah, right, that's a way
of understanding the whole ערי מקלט arei miklat and, you know, עד
עמדו לפני העדה למשפט, ad omdo lifnei ha'edah lemishpat, you take something
that was a blood feud or type of a ritual and you
try to bring it into the control of a legal system. So
the whole idea of סוטה, sotah, you know, in the Torah is
basically, you know, the husband suspects his wife and he's doing this
and he's going to, you know, and and this is a way
of testing and punishing her. There's no sense of any legal system
there. It's just the husband and the wife and שלעפינג schlepping her
to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. But you know what the rabbis
do is they introduce a whole legal apparatus. He has to warn
her in front of two witnesses. There have to be witnesses that
sees that she went in private with another man and so on.
So while it does not completely bring it into the legal system,
in the end it's through this ritual in the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, it's not through bringing testimony in a court, it is through
trying to make it something as a less about the pure whim
of the husband and something more about a certain amount of objective
evidence and witnesses and so on. So I raise that now, something
to keep in mind when we get to סוטה, sotah, but I
raise it now because here it's comparing it to משפט. mishpat. משפט
ביום mishpat bayom and סוטה ביום, sotah bayom, seeing the סוטה sotah
process as somewhat in under a משפט mishpat rubric. Okay. ולעריפת העגלה,
u'l'arifat ha'eglah, the breaking of the neck of the calf. אמרי דבי
רב ינאי, amri d'bei Rav Yannai, כפרה כתיב בה כקדשים, kaparah ksiv
bah k'kadshim, because it says כפר לעמך ישראל אשר פדית ה', kaper
l'amcha Yisrael asher padita Hashem, and an atonement, and we just know
all the atonements of sacrifices is the daytime, this too is the
daytime.
ולטהרת המצורע, u'letaharat hametzora, purifying the מצורע, metzora, דכתיב זאת תהיה תורת
המצורע ביום טהרתו, dichsiv zos tihyeh toras hametzora beyom taharato, the day
of his purification. Okay. כל הלילה כשר לקמיצת העומר kol halailah kasher
lekmitzat haomer and for
the הקטר חלבים, hakter chalavim, דאמר מר קצירה וספירה בלילה והבאה ביום,
da'amar mar ketzirah vesfirah balailah veha-vayah bayom, because we teach the cutting
and the counting is at night and the bringing of the עומר
omer is the day. Well that, that was very disappointing. Everything else
we had a פסוק, pasuk, here you're just telling me, trust me,
that's what we teach. So תוספות Tosafot or רש"י Rashi tells us,
yes, you go ahead and you look, you know, in, in the
גמרא elsewhere in מנחות, Menachot, then you'll see that the גמרא has
a whole like derivation of how we get to the idea that
the cutting is at night. So here, it's not that the גמרא
doesn't learn it from פסוקים, pesukim, we're just not bringing them in
here. But we do learn that out. Okay. תוספות Tosafot by the
way gets to it just as a little bit of a practical
thing. If you take a look at this little תוספות Tosafot on
כ"ף עמוד ב', kaf amud bet, we'll have like one extra minute,
he says כל הלילה כשר לקמיצת העומר. kol halailah kasher lekmitzat haomer.
So אמר רבינו תם amar Rabbeinu Tam שמי שכח לברך בלילה shemi
shachach levarech balailah for the ספירה, sefirah, because the גמרא say קצירה
וספירה בלילה, ketzirah vesfirah balailah, right, לא יברך ביום. lo yevarech bayom.
סתמא דהא סתמא דמתניתין דהידי כי סתמא דמנחות, stama de'ha stama dematnitin
dehidi ki stama de'menachot, and then he gets to the whole question
of what's the story בדיעבד if you cut it ביום. דתניא נקצר
ביום כשר, detanya niktzar bayom kasher, right, similar to the question like
before, you know, when we said okay, you start in the day,
but if you do it late you could do it at night
when we were talking about some some things like going to the
מקוה, certain things. What about by the קצירה? ketzirah? Let's say you
forgot the קצירת העומר ketzirat haomer at night, could you do it
the next morning? So there is an opinion that you can, מכל
מקום mikol makom he says סתמא דהכא עדיפא. stama de'hacha adifa. Here
it's a more absolute categorical, it only can be at night. And
if the קצירה ketzirah can only be at night and not the
following day, ספירה sefirah can only be at night and not the
following day. It wouldn't make sense. And then he gets on to
having other discussions, yeah, I don't know. Anyway, then he gets on
to questions about so if you miss a night and you count
in the day, could you count the next night with a ברכה?
berachah? All the types of issues that come up for us for
ספירת העומר, sefirat haomer, תוספות Tosafos has that whole discussion over here.
Okay. But he gets, focuses on the idea that since it says
דווקא davka at night that you cannot count the next day with
a ברכה. berachah. Okay. Back to our גמרא. ולהקטר חלבים ואיברים, u'lehakter
chalavim ve-eivarim,
so the burning of the fats and the limbs of the sacrifices,
דכתיב כל הלילה עד הבוקר, dichsiv kol halailah ad haboker, right, it
says by the fire pyre, that's fire pyre, by the pyre that's
on the altar it says, right, that you should burn it all
night till the morning, so that's quite explicit that that's the whole
night. Okay. זה הכלל, zeh haklal, this is the principle. דבר שמצוותו
ביום כשר כל היום. davar shemitzvato bayom kasher kol hayom. If it's
a day מצוה it's the whole day. זה הכלל לאתויי מאי, zeh
haklal l'atuyei mai, what is it coming to include? So רש"י Rashi
says הנה תפילין, hinei tefillin, which would be a good idea, but
that's what the גמרא says. לאתויי סידור בזיכין וסילוק בזיכין, l'atuyei siddur
bezichin vesilluk bezichin, maybe we're still in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
mentality, so it is the putting of the little cups of incense,
the little spoons of incense on the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim on
the table, you know, with the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim and removing
them, that you can, when you switch that, you know, which is
done on שבת, Shabbos, so you can do it anytime in the
day. And it's funny, you could have also said putting the bread
and removing the bread as we're about to see, כרבי יוסי, k'Rabbi
Yosi, דתניא detanya we saw in a ברייתא, braisa, רבי יוסי אומר,
Rabbi Yosi omer, סילוק את הישנה שחרית וסידור החדשה ערבית אין בכך
כלום. silluk es hayeshanah shacharit vesiddur hachadashah arvit ein bekach klum.
So this is not just the little things of incense, it's the
bread, you know, although the Torah says that the bread should be
on the table. table תמיד tamid constantly, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says
even if you took off the old loaves and you offered up
the incense the first thing in the morning and you put on
the new loaves and you put on the incense on the table
later in the day, in the afternoon, and there was a big
break of like 8 hours, 10 hours between them, that's still okay.
Why? It says ערבית, Arvis, right, means,
right, before sunset. Okay. ומה אני מקיים, Umani mekayem, what do I
do with the verse לפני השם תמיד Lifnei Hashem tamid or actually
לפני תמיד? Lifanai tamid? שלא יהא שולחן בלא לחם. Shelo yehe shulchan
belo lechem. It means that or שלא ילין shelo yalin is its
better version which is more precise. Right, it shouldn't go a night
without bread, but as long as it frames the beginning of the
day and the end of the day you're okay. So that's the
idea of כל היום. kol hayom. It could be, you might have
thought that no, it can't be later in the day. It has
to be right after you took off the old one. No, it
can be later in the day. Plus,
and how about דבר שמצותו בלילה כשר כל הלילה? davar shemitzvato balaylah
kasher kol halaylah? A night thing can be the whole night. לאתויי
מאי, Le'atuyei mai, what does this
include? לאתויי אכילת פסחים דלא כרבי אלעזר בן עזריה Le'atuyei achilat pesachim
delo keRabbi Elazar ben Azaria and not like רבי אלעזר בן עזריה.
Rabbi Elazar ben Azaria. דתניא, Detanya, we learned in a ברייתא, braita,
ואכלו את הבשר בלילה הזה. Ve'achlu et habasar balaylah hazeh. אמר רבי
אלעזר בן עזריה, Amar Rabbi Elazar ben Azaria, נאמר כאן בלילה הזה,
Ne'emar kan balaylah hazeh, it says here 'this night' you should eat
the meat, ונאמר להלן ועברתי בארץ מצרים בלילה
הזה. Vene'emar lehalan ve'avarti be'eretz Mitzrayim balaylah hazeh. I'll pass through מצרים
Mitzrayim this night, this night. מה להלן עד חצות, Mah lehalan ad
chatzos, the same way God the plague of בכורות, Bechoros, God's passing
through was at until midnight, אף כאן עד חצות. Af kan ad
chatzos. Here too it's until midnight and you can only eat the
meat until midnight, which is why some people make a point of
getting to the אפיקומן Afikoman by midnight. תוספות Tosafos. already mentions that.
Look at תוספות. Tosafos לאתויי אכילת פסחים דלא כרבי אלעזר בן עזריה.
Le'atuyei achilat pesachim delo keRabbi Elazar ben Azaria.
מכל מקום, Mikol makom, although the תוספות Tosafos before said we rule
the idea of דוקא davka קציר העומר ketzir ha'omer at night and
he ruled by this משנה over another discussion in מנחות, Menachos, here
he rejects this משנה and goes by רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rabbi
Elazar ben Azaria. Even though the גמרא says that we're rejecting רבי
אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi Elazar ben Azaria, נראה דהלכה כרבי אלעזר, nireh
dehalacha keRabbi Elazar, we rule like רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, דאיכא סתמא
בפרק ערבי פסחים, de'ika stama beperek arvei pesachim, there's another סתם משנה
stam mishnah דקאי כוותיה, dekay kivatei, דהפסח אחר חצות מטמא את הידיים.
dehapesach achar chatzos metamei es hayadayim. And then תוספות Tosafos spells out
the practical implications and then he says ואם כן, ve'im ken, it's
like five lines before the תוספות ends,
צריך למהר לאכול מצה בליל פסחים קודם חצות. tzarich lemaher leechol matzah
beleil pesachim kodem chatzos. You have to be make sure you eat
your מצה matzah before חצות chatzos ואפילו מצה של אפיקומן, vafilu matzah
shel afikoman, not only the first כזית kezayit of מצה matzah which
would be alright, that's already the מצוה. No, even the אפיקומן afikoman
שחיוב מצה בזמן הזה דאורייתא.
shechiyuv matzah bazman
hazeh de'oraisa. אבל בהלל של אחר האפיקומן Aval beHallel shel achar ha'afikoman
אין להחמיר כל כך שהרי מדרבנן היא. ein lehachmir kol kach sheharei
miderabbanan hi. Okay, so anyway, when we're learning פסחים, Pesachim, we could
have a longer discussion of does it have to be the אפיקומן,
afikoman, do we rule like רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi Elazar ben
Azaria, are there other ways of dealing with this, but anyway some
of that is linked to exactly this issue of מצותו כל הלילה.
mitzvato kol halaylah. הדרן עלך הקורא למפרע. Hadran alach Hakorei Lemafre'a.